[Music]
hey hey welcome to connecting with code
week two uh we're excited to have you
here uh we're gonna be using scratch
again just like we did uh in week one
um if you didn't see it there was a
whole week one which was an introductory
uh
series of videos that you scratch those
videos are focused for like a k
through three audience but to be honest
they're also for anyone that's never
coded before
this week is going to be like more
intense right so this uh this week is
for
fourth through eighth graders if you've
never coded before um and you're in that
that age range
uh then you're uh you're in the right
place if you're worried about your
coding you could go back and work a
couple of those videos from week one
just to kind of like mention that right
this series is also appropriate for
older people as well
uh people that just want to learn more
about scratch so what we're gonna do is
we're gonna build a game today
uh you're gonna follow along with me and
we're going to hopefully make some cool
things
i want to introduce my campers so i
brought two campers
that you might recognize from week one
love this guy introduce himself first
what's your name and how old are you
hello i am keegan fisher and
nine years old nine years old so he's
going to be going into fourth so he's
the
the age range at the bare minimum that
makes it in here
hi my name is mckinley fisher and i'm
11. cool and what grade are you going
into next year
sixth uh so these are uh my two campers
uh we're kind of on the younger end of
um
what this camp is really designed for uh
but we're gonna make it work right
so this material um consists of five
days so there's five different videos
today we're going to be doing something
called lawn mower so
lawnmower is uh today's week one monday
activity
uh tuesday is dino jump it's kind of
like the the no internet game
if you've ever played that in chrome uh
irish sheepdog
is wednesday slide puzzle it's probably
our biggest game it's going to be on
thursday
and then an advanced kaleidoscope so if
you were with us in week one
friday we did like an intro kaleidoscope
and we're going to be doing an advanced
kaleidoscope this week
i'd do some acknowledgments before we
get started this material was developed
by
me i'm a professor here at roles holmen
so this
camp is brought to you by rolls holmen
this year we're partnering with
mission college so this material was
co-developed by bob shaffer so you won't
see him on the camera here but we
developed the material together
so it's a partnership this year between
rolls-holman and mission college
to bring you this camp so let's take a
look at what we're going to build
together today
um so i'm going to start by showing you
the solution uh it's always kind of nice
to know
what our goal is this game is called
lawn mower
this is inspired by keegan by the way
he's the lawn mower in our family
and so let's go ahead and take a look at
the solution
by the way i'll make a link to the
solution available on the
website so connectingwithcode.org camp
and so you can go look at the solution
there if you want but i'm just going to
play it and you can watch it
so you can see that what happens is it
starts off by
planting grass and so the whole field
covered with grass
and then i'm controlling this mower with
the the keyboard keys
and i'm revealing a picture behind it
now this picture happened to be a fairly
grassy picture i've got one more to cut
up here
that was really loud and so you can see
that the idea of this game is that you
click the start button
uh and it plants all your grass um and
then it's got a hidden picture behind it
now sure enough this time it randomly
picked the same picture
i'm gonna stop it um and run it again
and so there's some hidden picture back
there
it is randomly picking a picture i
promise
all right so there it's finally a
different one and honestly i don't know
why it took so long to
get a different image but the idea of
this game is that you'll
make some secret image so you're going
to make a number of different wallpapers
to put back there
and then you're going to lawnmower to
reveal
to reveal the solution right i mean each
time it should be
different and you can make fun messages
for people that you think are going to
play your game so let's say you're going
to show this
to your mom moms always like messages
specific to them
and so you might say i love you mom
so that's kind of how the game works uh
makes sense you guys ready to get
started
so normally uh with scratch what we do
is we go visit scratch.mit.edu so i'm
just going to type this in
scratch.mit.edu
and we typically sign in if you already
have a sign in with scratch
then use it if you don't you just have
to sign in over here so
if you haven't ever signed in it'll
probably look like this
and you'll have to click on join scratch
if you don't have an account
if you do have an account click on sign
in pause the video if you don't have an
account and make one
you don't have to validate the email
address if you don't want
it'll ask you to validate an email
address if you can do that go ahead and
do it but you can't make public products
until you validate your email address so
just kind of get that worked out
now normally what we do in scratch i'm
just going to kind of show you this
really quickly
is we click on create and we just start
creating a game in scratch
my hope is that you've probably already
done something in scratch before this
camp this is kind of an advanced camp
but if you haven't it's okay i'm just
going to quickly tell you about the
environment
so the environment is set up in a couple
different sections
the section over here is the stage this
is like where your code
runs where things happen below the stage
are the different
sprites in your game some people call
them actors so here i've got a cat as an
actor in my game
and i can move him around on the stage
and then the cat has
code that you can write for the cat
that's obviously why we're
using scratch because it involves a lot
of code it can have
costumes which are different images for
the sprites
and then he can have sounds that he
knows how to play just to really briefly
do something let's
drag over one piece of code
and to run it you can double click on it
that's like one way to run it
it's kind of the worst way to run it but
it is one way to run it
you can also go to events here you can
see that there's a number of different
code blocks
and they're color coordinated you can
either click on these to get around
or you can scroll through here to find
it if you go to events
and grab when green flag clicks that's
typically how these programs start
and so now when i click the green flag
you can see that he goes
typically your programs will have loops
so i'm going to just quickly grab a
forever loop here
and i'm going to stick it around that
one you can see that scratch
is more kid friendly than regular
program language because you
you drag and drop the code instead of
actually like typing it
and then just to put one more command in
here i'm going to find one that says
if on edge balance so right now if i run
this program you can see that it makes
my cat go back and forth forever
that is typically how we start programs
we start from a blank slate
we add sprites we add code we build
things up
for today's lesson this is a more
advanced lesson we're going to start
with
a starter project so instead of
making you download the images for like
the lawnmower and the grass
i'm going to give you a starting project
and we're going to learn a
ton of things today this is just kind of
a list of the learning objectives for
today
learning about the environment we kind
of just did that learning about flow
control statements
learning how to make clones even
mckinley hasn't made clones she'll be
excited to learn about clones
and lots of good stuff with scratch so
to start things off what you're going to
need to do
is you're going to need to remix the
project that i've got here this project
is called
lawnmower starting code so you're going
to have to go to this url
this url i'll make it available in the
email that i send out
i'll make it available on the
connectingwithcode.org
camp page so you can find it there also
put it in the description of this video
if all those things fail just type it
right it's not that hard to type
when you go to uh so i'm just going to
go and close this one
when you go to this page it should look
like this so to say lawnmower starting
code
created by fisher.ds that's me you're
going to have to click on remix
now what you happens with remix is it
makes a copy of this project
from fischerds and it brings it into
your account
so now you have remixed this project
it also makes the name lawnmower
starting code remix
let's go ahead and change that so let's
just make it lawnmower
and that's that's a fine name if you
just want to delete what's there if you
wanted to type something else you could
but i'm just going to say a lawnmower
whenever you get code from someone else
the first thing you need to do is you
need to understand
what you've got so i'm going to go and
zoom in a little bit here so you can see
it better
so what we've got is we've got two
sprites uh one sprite
is called robot mower the other sprite
is called
grass square you can see that robot
mower and grass square they have no code
right so there's no code that we're
giving you so really we just wanted to
give you some images
we've also got a backdrop over here the
backdrop has no code as well
and the backdrop you can see has two
costumes in it uh one
is called a lawnmower connecting with
code and then the other is just this
blank xy grid so we've given you
two uh two backdrops in here now later
in
in today's project you're going to
create a bunch more backdrops because
these are going to be like the secret
backdrops
that you can reveal you can make two or
three and that's plenty
but you can make 10 if you really want
it and so just know these are the secret
things
that kind of make your game fun for
others for now though go back to the xy
grid alright so that's the the sprite so
we've got a mower
we've got grass we've got backdrops
and we're ready to to write some code so
to get started i want you to click on
the lawnmower
you know you've got the lawnmower
selected because his icon shows up here
and also he's got a blue line around him
and then
you could change his costumes or sounds
but obviously we want the code
so we've got a couple different goals
for this game
our first goal is actually going to
start with the mower itself
and so the mower itself needs to move
so you can see that the mower always
moves right
and then what we do is with the left and
right arrow keys
we change the direction that the mower
is going
and so that's the that's the goal of
this project
so the mower let's start with the basics
let's start with
events when green flag clicks
so most projects start this way this is
kind of like the
the main function that gets called so
when the green flag is clicked people
will expect that's how they start your
game
what i want to do when the green flag is
clicked is i want to make sure that my
mower always starts in that corner
so i'm going to go to motion and i'm
gonna grab
a go to xy the nice thing about this
command
is that it knows where your mower is
currently at um it's currently at
negative 200
uh negative 150 and it's actually just
going to go to
negative 200 negative 150. the next
thing i want to do
is i want to put on a point in direction
of 90. so when you run your program now
it looks like nothing happens
but if you move your mower somewhere
different and then run your program
it's going to snap to that location so
far so good
let's see now if we can make this guy
start to move
so the movement is going to need to
happen uh forever
so the first thing i grab is a forever
loop i always joke with my younger kids
that it's uh
really like improper to tell some human
to do something forever but in code it
happens all the time so forever
uh do this thing and forever what we
want to do
is we want to uh move so we're going to
have move 3 in here
if you were to run it right now it would
work fine except for you can't steer
right so you could run it it would do
that you could take it back and run it
again
so we need to be able to steer using the
left arrow key and right arrow key
so we need to know if somebody's
pressing the left arrow key
or the right arrow key and i mean you
kind of heard the command we're going to
need
in the words there so go to control
and find an if statement again if you're
completely new to coding
some of these things will seem like a
flood of information
but if you've done anything with scratch
before you've probably seen if
statements
the way an if statement works is it says
if
this condition is true so this diamond
means like condition
then execute the code that's in here and
currently there's no code in there
i put two of them on there because i
know i need a left and a right
let's do the conditions first conditions
are very often
in sensing sometimes they're in
operators we'll get that later
and in sensing what we want to do is we
want to find the right condition you'll
notice the conditions are the diamonds
here
so there's like a touching a touching
color
a color touching color all these things
here's the one we want
key space pressed so go ahead and drag
one of these and drop it over
by the way you know it's going to go in
there whenever the outline goes white
right so some people try to like put the
middle of it in there and it doesn't
work
you got to kind of put the edge in there
and when it goes white you drop it in
now obviously space is not what we want
but that's why there's this little drop
down arrow on here so click the drop
down arrow
and change the top one to left arrow uh
and the bottom one to
right arrow so when we press the left
arrow we want to turn a few degrees to
the left
and then the opposite with the right
movement you'll kind of get used to this
it's going to happen over in motion
and so in motion a left turn it kind of
looks like a counterclockwise turn
so that is the left direction
and then the right direction is the
opposite right so
left and right and the amount that i'm
going to turn is just 5 and 5.
and so now if you run your game you
should be able to use the arrow keys
to drive your lawnmower around your lawn
and so it should be
i don't know a pretty successful little
fun game
eventually you will get bored of driving
your lawnmower around
because there's nothing to collect or
nothing to do i could probably drive it
around for a while but eventually i'd
get bored
i can make it do donuts for a while
so what we need to do is we need this
lawn mower
to actually like collect grass right so
you can see that the first thing that
happens is the game is
all the grass gets planted and then the
lawn mower starts collecting it
so i think that we're ready to start
planting some grass
in order to plant grass if we kind of
watch it here you can see that it does
a clone of the sprite called grass
and it puts it on it does the whole top
row and then the second row and then the
third row
and it does it so fast it's almost like
magic
it's not magic you have to code it up to
make it work
so what i want to do is i want to start
with a little bit of math
because math is going to tell us where
these
pieces of grass need to go it's going to
tell us how many
are in each row it's going to tell us
how many columns there are
and so we need to kind of do some math
to understand what's going on
so the first thing that we need to do is
we need to understand this piece of
grass
so how big is this piece of grass
in here it says it's size 100 that
doesn't really tell you how big it is
the costume over here says it's 60 by
60.
oh that that actually does tell you how
big it is
and in fact if you look at this grid
this grid shows you how big the whole
stage is
and you can see that here's uh 100 here
and so it's just a little bit more than
half so it's 60 by 60.
so that's our first piece of knowledge
so how big is the tile
so what we're going to do is we're going
to go through some slides to kind of do
the math
to make sure we understand things and
then we're going to get started
in writing the code and i'm going to use
a white board here
all right so i got my white board uh and
now i'm free to draw on things so this
square
um we know that it is 60 uh by 60 so
that's
that's how big it is we're going to need
to know some other things
in addition to the square we're going to
need to know um how
big the overall grid is uh and so i'll
kind of ask my campers
um how wide do you guys think this grid
is shut it out if you think you know the
answer
240. so 240 was the first guess 240 is a
very reasonable guess
i'll say that 240 is almost right but
it's not quite right
any other guesses
so i'll give you a hint this side is
positive 240.
that side is negative 240. so how big is
the whole thing
480 480 that's right so this grid
is uh and i just kind of write it up
here it's 480 pixels wide total
so that's something that we're going to
need to know uh let's do the same
thing uh with the height how tall is
this grid from top to bottom
360.
all right yep 360 uh is correct uh so
the y is 180
it goes to a negative 180 oh that's
really hard to read down there
and so this thing is 360 tall
so we're just kind of like gathering
some information
so the next question is just so we
understand it how many
will fit left to right so this
square is 60 there's 480 total so
your division skills are going to get
tested here so how many squares do we
think are going to fit
left to right keegan uh not quite
[ __ ] so
so her guess was 80. eight
eight eight yeah yep no problem so
our goal um is to fit on here
eight squares across so if we
were to kind of like divvy this thing up
um you know we could divide it here
and here i rise my marker is not great
but there's going to be
eight different um
squares uh split up in here maybe i'll
get a better marker here in a little bit
uh next question how many fits uh top to
bottom oh shoot i jumped to the wrong
page i guess i've got the answer here
how many will fit top to bottom if it's
360.
keegan can you read the screen six yeah
that's right
so our goal that's a marker um our goal
is to get
um eight of them uh across and then six
of them from top to bottom
so it looks like there's going to be
kind of like a a row here a row there
a row here so our goal is to to make all
that happen
now we're going to start putting them in
one at a time right so we're going to
start putting them in we're going to put
in this one first
and then this one second and then this
one third fourth fifth
sixth seventh eighth you get the idea
i'm not gonna label all these
how many are we gonna have total what's
the bottom number here can anybody
figure out what we're going to have
total
48 48 that's correct um and so somehow i
got off there
uh that's 15 and 16. so there's going to
be 48 squares total
they're going to be set up with 8 in
each row
and there's going to be six rows total
now we've got to do some harder math
so where does the first one go so in
scratch what you care about is you
care about the center of the sprite
so our first one that we're going to put
in goes right there
so this edge has an x value of negative
240.
the overall box is 60 wide
so what is the x value uh right here
so how much do we have to move over from
negative 240
um half of the box and so what value
in the x is that right there you got it
all right
way to go keegan all right so keegan
just got it studied again for us keegan
negative 210 right so it just changes
that uh
by by 30. so negative 210 that's going
to be an important number
so the x center is negative 210 of that
first tile
what's the y so the y up here is
180 at the top and of course we have to
come
down by 30. so what is the y value of
this first dial
150. 150. since we got this one all
right so
um that's our math right so this this
square right here
um this slide right here as soon as i
erase all this junk
kind of summarizes our math so we're
going to have a total of
eight squares coming across
and we're going to have six squares up
and down
and the first one is going to go at
negative 210
uh positive 150. so that um is kind of
our strategy in our plan
so how do we make that happen um so what
we're gonna have to do is we're gonna
have to go back into our code and we're
gonna make
clones of the sprite uh and we're gonna
put the first one there
and we're going to see if we can get
that to work and then after we put the
first one on
we'll try to put on the whole first row
and then after we put on the whole first
row then we'll put on the whole thing
sound good so let's go back to our code
all right so let's see if we can
jump over into our code uh and and make
this thing work
so how do we get a square to show up
there well one way we could
we could do it is we could just put it
there right uh so you know we could go
until it's at the right spot so negative
210 positive 150
and then we could like duplicate it and
make another one and put it in the right
spot
that that would totally work um but
that's not how
computer scientists work right so if
you're making
um you know multiples of something but
it's really kind of the same thing
what you want to do is you want to make
a clone of it and in fact i don't care
where the original starts at all because
eventually i'm going to hide the
original
so i'm just going to put the original in
some random spot and what i want to do
is i want to create clones of it
and move it to a spot so let's do this
let's go over to our stage so click on
the stage here
go into the code on the stage and what
the stage is going to do is the stage is
going to be responsible for planting all
the grass
so let's grab a wind green flag clicked
for the stage
and what he's going to do is he's going
to plant grass
so to plant grass what you want to do is
you want to say create
clone of grass square
so if you were to run this program now
what it would do is it would create a
clone of the grass square
it's very unexciting because the place
where it created the clone
was in the same spot as the original
does that make sense so there's actually
two of them now there's the original
and the clone so we need to create a
graph square somewhere else
right so let's make some variables so
you can make variables in scratch
variables are very powerful in
programming they let you just save off a
number so that it's referenced by a name
click on variables and we're going to
make two variables
click on make a variable the first
variable is going to be called
grass x so this is the x value
for the grass and then the next variable
is going to be called
grass y so
grass x and grass y you can probably
guess what these variables are going to
get used for
variables in scratch you can easily
display them on the screen if you want
but you don't have to so i'm going to
click on this checkbox here
and what that does is that just makes it
to where it's not displayed on the
screen
so no big deal i just i don't i don't
need it displayed on the screen you
still have the variable if it's not
displayed
um i just don't need the display so
here's my goal
before i say clone graphs i'm going to
set
the x and the y so i'm going to set
grass x to negative 210
and i'm going to set grass y to positive
150.
so those variables are going to get used
they're not used yet they're going to
get used
to tell this clone where to go right so
i'm going to
create x y and a clone
now i've got to go into the into the
grass square to make it actually use
those variables
so the stage right now is fine i'm gonna
move from the stage
to the grass square you'll notice that
every sprite has its own code the stage
has its own code and you can hop around
between them uh however you want right
so like our mower has a bunch of things
done
our grass square doesn't have anything
yet let's write our graph square
so let's go to events normally
you would use when green flag clicked
that is not the case for clones
clones are a little bit different so
clones you need to scroll down into
control
and find when i start as clone
it's kind of a neat event so whenever i
start as a clone
what do i do well the first thing i want
to do is i want to set my x and y
using those variables so i go to motion
i go to set go to xy
and i don't want to type in a number i
want to use those variables so i go to
variable
and i use grass x and i use grass y
so now when i run it my backdrop is
going to set grass x grass y
it's going to say create clone of graph
square and glass squares are going to go
to that position so if i run it now you
can see that there's now a grass square
up at the top so pretty exciting i know
right
now something that happens a lot with
clones is
we don't actually want the original and
so the original
actually we want to hide it all together
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to
hide the original
you can do this in code if you wanted
but actually it's easier you can
actually just click on this little like
no eyeball button and now it's hidden
that worked but now your clone is also
hidden so now we've got to show
our clone does that make sense so for
the when i start as clone i want it to
show
show is in looks um and i scroll down to
and i'm going to put it after the go to
xy
i could put it before it wouldn't really
matter there's just some chance you'd
see it move
but i don't think you'd even see it so
now if i run it you can see that my
uh grass square starts up there
so we have successfully created one
grass square um if you go up and try to
mow it
nothing's gonna happen right so like uh
it looks like the mower goes under it
even
um and it's not surprising that nothing
happens because we haven't like made
anything happen
but we've got a cool setup now
so now uh let's go back to the backdrop
so if we wanted to make another graph
square
i could um duplicate it you can do this
too just to prove that it works uh but
we're
this is not going to be our final
solution we could just march over to the
next spot so if it was at
negative 210 and we need to move over 60
what's 260 sorry
what's 60 moved over [ __ ] do you know
that one so negative 210
we're going to add 60 to it and go over
here so it's negative 210
plus 60. negative 150 negative 150
that's right
so i could do this um and it would make
two squares now there's a glitch right
you're like wait a minute dr fisher you
just said that this was gonna work
um here's here's the deal this is this
is what's called a bug
right um it actually is so fast that it
makes this one
and it says hey start making this and
then it starts making this one and they
actually both
got set to the second coordinate so to
fix this bug
sometimes that happens we need a very
very short time delay
after we make a clone so i'm going to go
into control
i'm going to grab weights and i'm going
to make it very very short
so i'm going to do like 0.01
so very very short delay all right by
the way i just went and helped keegan
with a problem he had a problem where he
was accidentally setting grass x
twice instead of x and y code you'll
find
is very very good at doing what you tell
it to do
and you have to make sure that you tell
it to do the right things right
so x y x y so this worked fine
by the way you'll notice i didn't
actually need to wait at the end because
it because it was done
all right so now our goal is to make a
whole row of them
right um and we could obviously keep
duplicating this but eventually we would
have 48
of these things right so we don't really
want to do that so what we want to do is
we want to make a row
because i like to teach you things we're
going to also teach you about a function
so we're going to make a function which
we can call um and we'll just call
make a row and it'll just do it so to
to make a function it's in scratch it's
called a block so go to my blocks
click on make a block
and we'll make this function um we'll
call it plant
uh row so just plant row so it's kind of
like a verb like plant
um and then the thing that you're going
to plant is a is a whole row
plant row is our function and so our
goal is that we're going to use some of
this code over here
inside of our function to make it work
so um let's go ahead and figure out what
code needs to go
into the function so i kind of
disconnected it over here by the way to
to call the function
you'll just say when the green flag is
pressed
plant a row so a row is is only about
x's right so really what i want to do is
i want to put
things about x's over here so the the
grass
x i want to put it over here the grass
y however i want to like set before i
plant the row so
grass y says like what height should i
plant this row at
so i'm saying at 150 plant a row
and so to plant a row what we really
want to do is we want to make a loop
so loops are in control does anybody
remember how many grass squares we have
in a single row how many do we put
across
eight that's right so i'm going to grab
a repeat
of eight um and what i want to do
is i want to create a clone of the grass
square
and then to fix that little bug i want
to wait for a second so
i'm going to set the x to the starting
value
i'm going to plant a grass i'm going to
wait this long
and then after i plant that grass i'm
going to change the x
by some amount so i'm going to scoot it
over before the next one is planted
so go into variables and we want to
change
the x uh by some amount
um any guesses as to what the amount's
going to be
30. so the first guess is 30.
you said 30 so i'm going to try 30 first
so if i run it now
it planted them only 30 apart yeah so we
want we want 60.
so this is kind of fun so we can um
tell the y where it's at and then we can
call plant row now we could
this is again i'm just kind of like
showing you something you could do we
could
change the y to a new value and call
plant row again
so i'm going to bring the y down by 60.
so keegan this is your math problem
150 minus 60.
90. 90. that's right so
90. so you can see that right now i'm
planting a row at 150
and then i'm planting a row at 90. now
to be honest this wouldn't be too bad to
do
there's only six of them coming this
wouldn't be too bad to just repeat
but we're computer scientists right
that's not how computer scientists roll
we make loops right um so how many rows
are their total anybody want to say what
that number is
six six yep so we're going to grab a
repeat six
um and what we're going to do is we're
going to plant a row
um at a given y so i'll tell you what
i'm going to clean up some things here
so we're going to set the y to be 150
that's where we decided that we'd start
at the top
if you remember our our math over here
that's the first one
um and then we're going to plant a row
there and then we're going to change the
y
um and repeat it six times so take a
minute
um and see if you can finish uh finish
the thing that's missing here
so we're setting it to 150 and then
we're going to repeat something six
times we're planting a row
but after we plant the first row we want
to we want to change the y by some
amount
see if you can figure out what it is uh
play with it and see if you can get the
whole field to show up
all right so for my campers uh mckinley
uh knocked it out and keegan says
um there's a lot of code and you're
going really fast right um
you're maybe somewhere in the middle so
the y of 150 plants a row here
and what i want to do is i want to go
into variables and i then want to after
i plant a row i want to change the y
um and i want to bring it down uh by 60.
now um in the y if we want to come down
it's currently 150.
we want to come down 60 that's a
negative 60.
so you can kind of see how i suppose
that see if it works with loops
you can make your code much shorter than
if you had written the whole thing
so now you can see that it plants the
row by row
all the grass squares now it did plant
it right on top of my lawn mower
uh which i guess is a feature eventually
the lawnmower is going to going to cut
the grass
now one thing that i don't like is see
how my lawnmower is like mowing while
the grass is being planted
i actually don't like that i want the
lawnmower
to just be hidden while the grass is
planted it'll actually make my computer
faster too right
so here's what i want to do after i
finish planting all the grass
i want to broadcast an event that says
i'm done planting the grass right so
this is how one sprite
can communicate with another you
broadcast an event and a broadcast event
it's kind of like screaming a message
like
i'm done right so real loud so go into
events
and find where it says broadcast message
one
and put it down here at the bottom so
it's making all the rows and then when
it's done it's going to broadcast
something
right now it's going to broadcast
message one that's not a very good name
let's let's call it like done
planting right so you can
write the word done planting any way you
want you could say done
and planting you could you could say it
like that i choose
to name my variables my messages
my anything using a style that computer
programmers use
it's what's called camel case and so
things start with a lowercase variable
and then there's no spaces between words
you just use a capital
to indicate that a new word started so
done planting there's
nothing special about that i'm just
showing you cool things that computer
scientists do right
so i broadcast done planting and then
over here in the lawn mower
you can see that he does a lot of things
when the green flag is clicked
here's what i'm going to do i'm going to
say
when i receive done planting so all this
stuff
can happen when he receives done
planting
so i can move him over here in fact if i
want to i could go a step farther so you
could run him now and he'll just kind of
be stationary
until it's done planting if you wanted
to you could go one step farther you
could go into looks
and you could hide him when the green
flag is clicked
and then show him only when he's ready
to start moving
right i personally choose to put the
show after his x and y have been set
just so there's no chance of like seeing
him in two places
but now if you run it you can see he's
just not there and then he
starts moving um once all the grass is
done
now you can't see him moving because
he's underneath my grass
i'm kind of surprised that he's
underneath my grass but it'll it'll be
fine
so things are going really really well
by the way
in coding you should always remember to
save but scratch does save automatically
for you
if you ever want to save though you can
click on file
save now and it'll save it for you so
we're doing great the question is what
now
right so right now
um when the lawnmower goes he's
underneath the grass
but you can see in the real game when he
touches a grass square
it should go away so whenever you're
coding you have to figure out whose
responsibility is that so who's
responsible
for detecting when the grass is touching
the mower
oh that scared me who's responsible for
detecting uh when the grass is touching
the mower
and then making it disappear you could
put that responsibility on either side
but since it's the grass the tiding
i'm going to put that responsibility on
the grass right
so let's go to the grass so right now
the grass isn't doing anything the grass
just shows up and then it just sits
there like this
and so really what the grass needs to do
is the grass needs to detect
if it's touching the mower and if it's
touching the mower
then it needs to hide right so let's go
uh
to control one mistake that people do
all the
time is they stick an if statement
straight on the bottom here
um that would be pointless um and the
reason it would be pointless
is because it would literally check it
one time when the program runs
and then never again we want to forever
check for that so i'm going to grab a
forever loop first
and then i'm going to put an if
statement inside of that so i want to
forever
check if i'm touching the mower
and if i am touching the mower then i
want to do stuff right
and so how do i detect if i'm touching
the mower it's one of these conditions
it's in sensing and the one that you
want is actually
touching mouse pointer which is kind of
crazy but it's got a drop down arrow
and so we want to say if i'm touching
the robot mower
so now the grass it's his responsibility
to check if he's touching the robot
mower if he
is touching the robot mower we want to
score point basically so that we can
keep track of how much has been mowed
and we also want to go away so those are
the two things we want to do
let's go ahead and score a point first
so to score a point we're going to need
a variable so i clicked on variables
make a variable and so you can name this
variable whatever you want
um i'm going to call mine grass cuts
you could call it num grass cut
whatever whatever you want to do this
variable you'll notice that i chose to
name differently
and that's because it will be visible uh
like like on my screen
so if it is visible uh then i try to
make it like human readable right so num
grass cut
so it's going to show up up here i could
hide it if i wanted but actually for now
i'm going to make it visible
all right so whenever you make a
variable there's a couple things you
have to do
you have to create it so i've created it
here
you have to set it to zero somewhere or
set it to some initial value somewhere
and then you also have to increment it
really quick
i'm going to come back to this code i'm
going to go into the backdrop
and i'm going to grab a set
num grass cuts to zero over here now
i could have reset this variable in a
couple of different places um i chose to
do it over on the stage so
i start off saying num grass cuts zero
uh on on the stage i think that makes
the most sense and then we've got to
increment it
so now i hop back over you can see i hop
between code all the time
hop back over to my graphs and i'm gonna
change
numb grass cut by one and so it's going
to increment
how much grass i cut the other thing i
want to do is i want to
hide this piece of grass
what i'm going to actually do instead of
just hiding it i'm going to delete it
go into control and find
delete this clone so you can see that
when i start as clone
i do all these things and if i touch the
lawnmower
then i delete myself so now for the
first time ever we should be deleting
grass right
so if i hit the green flag i can now
like mow the lawn
which is cool things are going
really really well so the next thing i
want to do
is i want to change the background image
so you can see that right now i'm mowing
and my user is not at all surprised or
delighted
because the background image is just
always this grid right
if i run it again it's still just the
grid
also you'll notice that nothing happens
when the game wins it was playing that
super loud sound for me earlier
so we want to create some backdrops
that will surprise and delight our user
so here's what we want to do go into
backdrops
the first thing i want to do is i want
to create a few different backdrops so
go into backdrops
you can see that right now there's one
it's called lawnmower connecting with
code
so this is one of the things that we
might put in there's the secret backdrop
but we can put more on here as well so
do this for me
in the lower left where it says choose
backdrop just click on this circle
um and you can put in any backdrop
that you'd like so i'll put on hearts
uh you could choose to put a message in
this heart
so you could say love you mom
or dad we don't have to be specific
about about one or the other
um we haven't talked to you about
drawing yet but i think
that it's fun to just try to figure
things out um so so there's one
that one says love you mom i'm gonna
make another one
maybe i'll make a jungle
you could put things on here if you
wanted you could put text on here so
this one i'm going to say
welcome to the jungle
by the way you can do things like
resizing uh you can play with different
colors on things
you could do uh whatever you wanted um
i'm
not planning in this lecture to help you
make cool backgrounds
because i just want you to play right
and so pick whatever you think would be
a back
uh ground that's fun uh maybe you'll
give a message like can
we get into the pool so you could say
hey mom play this game
or hey dad play this game and then it
would expose this question of uh can we
get into the pool
so you can see that right now i have
four possible
hidden backdrops i could keep making
more
they don't have to be customized right
so i could just like put on one of these
images
if you know how to do it you can also
get things from the internet again not
going to show you this today
and then you could upload that image
here so you can put like a picture of
yourself on there
that'd be kind of fun to do and make as
many
uh as you want i currently have uh
two through seven as options so i think
that that's
enough for me so i'm gonna give my
campers just a minute to make a few more
uh and then we're gonna move forwards uh
with the code
all right so my campers went in uh and
they added a bunch of uh
grids uh let's look at the solution real
quick to review how this is gonna work
so
while you're drawing the the grid um
it's some backdrop
and then as soon as the grid is done
it switches to some secret backdrop
right so it's while you're drawing it's
a grid
and then it changed to some secret this
one always confuses me
and so that's our goal so let's go into
our code on our backdrop
so backdrop code so when the green flag
is clicked i want to start off on the
grid
so i'm going to go to looks i'm going to
put in a
switch backdrop to xy grid
so that's kind of like my first my first
grid
um and so right now if i run it you can
see it switches to that grid but it's
going to stay as that grid
based on the code that i have right now
so let's
after it's done drawing let's switch it
right
and so the the moment when it's done
drawing the grid is down here
so just before um
oops uh let's grab it right there just
before we broadcast this event
let's switch the backdrop to something
different now we could
uh hard code that but then that wouldn't
be random right so we could say like
switch to hearts
but now every time you play the game um
it's going to switch it to
uh to your heart right so we want to
randomly pick
that background and so that's where
operators come in
and so we want um n operators pick
random now one nice thing about costumes
is you can refer to them by name so this
one was called hearts
uh this one's called xy grid or number
right
so i could also say switch to number one
and that would be the xy grid
or number two so what i want to do is i
want to decide how many
random things do i have so for me uh my
first value is a two
so i want to pick a number between two
um
and then for me it looks like i've got a
seven in here as well
so pick something between two uh and
seven
so it'll always be the xy grid while
it's drawing
so i it's always the expert grid while
it's drawing but then after that
uh it's random it's random number
generator is not amazing
you might see the same thing a couple
times uh but right now it's the heart
and then if i run it again this time it
looks like it's
the jungle right so it says welcome to
the jungle so it's kind of a neat little
uh reveal game by the way when you stop
the game
uh if you stop it manually it will just
show you the rest of the board
i consider that a feature right so um
not not worried about it
but that is how the game works so every
time it's different
now last feature that we'd like to add
is when you finish
mowing the lawn i feel like something
should happen
right so like i finished uh getting the
last square
but right now in our game nothing will
happen right so we hit
num grass cut 48 um but nothing
nothing happened um and as you might
recall from the solution it plays that
really loud scary sound you guys
remember that
yes so let's let's add code this will be
our last feature
that does something when the number of
grass cut is equal to 48.
so somebody has to be responsible for
this right who's going to be checking uh
if the num
grass cut is equal to 48 we could put it
in a number of places
we could let the grass check for it that
seems a little strange
we could let the background check for it
that would that would be okay
the only thing about the backdrop is it
doesn't have a forever loop right so
we'd have to make one so what i'm going
to do is i'm going to have the
robot mower check for it just because
he's got a forever loop he's always
present
so i'm going to go into the robot mower
and he's going to be the one
that checks for game over a check
is a control if statement so go ahead
and grab
an if statement here and so
if some condition is true then
run this code in here normally our
conditions have been sensing conditions
but this time we're going to do
something different we're going to go
into operators
and we're going to find the equals
operator
and so we're going to say if the thing
on the left is equal to
the thing on the right then run this
code and so one of them should be the
variable
num grass cut and then the other should
be the number 48
so 48 is the special number which means
you've cut
all the grass so when that happens
we want to play a sound if you go into
the sounds tab
you can see that the lawnmower right now
apparently he doesn't have any sounds
that he knows how to play
so let's pick a sound that we want him
to play so to pick a sound i'm going to
click on choose a sound down here
and the one that i played in the
solution
is ta-da so i'm going to pick ta-da
again if you would like to pick a
different sound you just kind of hover
over it
and it'll play it for you and you can
listen to
uh to the different sounds but i think
ta-da is a pretty good one if i hover
over it
you can see it's this nice loud ta-da so
once you've found the one you want
uh just click in the middle of it and
it'll
add it to this sprite sound library
so now this sprite is capable of playing
the ta-da sound now we've got to do it
in code right
so go into code go into sound
and uh find where it says play
sound ta-dah until done
so i'm going to play sound ta-dah until
done
now after i play the sound i want to
finish the game right so the game's
going to be over so i'm going to go to
control
and i'm going to grab a stop all
so this is going to play a sound
really loud and then it's going to shut
the game down so the game is over at
that point
i think i'm going to run it and see if
it works if it does work
then i'm gonna call myself pretty happy
about it
so uh to test it i kind of have to just
do
all the mowing so i'm gonna mo mo mo
by the way it's your game if you wanna
speed up the mower a lot of people like
to do that feel free
to go ahead so all right let's talk
about 44 and get the last bit
that was some seriously loud to dying uh
totally worked
so it says ta-da and then the game
finished
my game is done what i like to do is my
last step is i like to share it publicly
so i'm going to click on this share
button up here you'll only get a share
button
if you have created an account and
validated an email address
but i like to do that and then right now
in the instructions it says use the
arrow keys to mow the lawn
i think that those are lovely
instructions that must have come from
the remix
and what i love to do is that this url
now
is something that you could share with
friends and family
so you can share this with whoever you
want so you just copy this url and send
an email to grandma
and say check out the cool game that i
made alright so
i've got a few closing remarks i want to
make but actually i want to see how my
campers
are doing first so we're going to go see
how mckinley and keegan did
and we're going to check out their games
and see how they came out
all right keegan let's go ahead and see
a demo of yours
so it looks like you've got um the lawn
set up which is great
yeah the only real area for creativity
in this game
is what is the like hidden thing behind
it some games will have an opportunity
for a lot of creativity
but this one uh is really just the the
background image so looks like keegan
has a secret passage as one of his
background images
i'm sure he's got quite a few let's go
and have him finish
just so we can hear his sound lovely
um great i'm going to click play again
just so we can see that switches to a
different image and then we'll let [ __ ]
go
uh so he's got some other image looks
like that was the connecting with code
one great
all right mckinley
i don't know why i did that
so a bug in there that i'm sure that
we'll be able to fix
um but it looks like she has a
functional
lawnmower game um it looks like she's
got a lot of fun background image
it looks like she made one wow very
complex did you make that yourself
mckinley
it was on a different game i made
she used the kaleidoscope version to
make that for herself great
uh great you guys have fun oh there's
your kaleidoscope program where you make
backgrounds
do you guys have fun with the lawnmower
game today yes
is the uh challenge of the games this
week quite a bit higher than it was last
week
all right so uh we hope that you had fun
today uh the real goal is that you learn
that that coding is fun
and that you can do this you can see how
we used a lot of math skills math and
code
man they go hand in hand right we
learned about doing things in sequence
we learned about how different sprites
have their own code
and we also learned one of the best
tricks is that you can have one sprite
with many many clones of it so it was a
huge first day
i chose to put a big one right off the
go because this week is going to be a
little bigger right
when you watch these videos it might
take you a few settings to try to get
through them
but my hope is that you learn a lot
and you uh will be able to apply these
skills uh to your own scratch games one
day
uh we hope you enjoyed being with us uh
we've got a lot of additional fun
uh ins set for you for the rest of the
week uh and we can't wait to see you
then
bye
[Music]